A Guide to the Louis G. Cowan World War II Propaganda Collection, ca. 1942-1946
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Louis G. Cowan World War II Propaganda Collection, ca. 1942-1946
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11569
ca. 190 items (1.5 Hollinger boxes and oversize materials)
These papers consist of the World War II American propaganda collection of Louis G. Cowan, ca. 1942-1946, including posters, pamphlets, booklets, magazines, cutouts and miscellany collected by Cowan while associated with the Overseas Branch of the Office of War Information. There is Allied propaganda material in Arabic, Chinese, Dutch, English, French, German, Greek, Icelandic, Italian, Japanese, Norwegian, Polish, Russian, and Spanish.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the University of Virginia Library by his daughter, Holly Cowan Shulman, Charlottesville, Virginia, in December 1999.
Biographical/Historical Information
Louis G. Cowan (1909-1976), son of Jacob J. and Hetty Smitz Cowan, began his work with the Overseas Branch of the Office of War Information as a liaison to the OWI from the army. Then he became head of the Radio Program Bureau where he stayed from July 1943 until 1944. Taking charge of the New York office, Cowan directed operations to Europe, Africa, and the Middle East.
Cowan was a public relations expert (President of the Louis G. Cowan Company, 1931-1941) and radio producer (Louis G. Cowan, Inc., radio and TV productions, 1946-1955) who was first exposed to the world of propaganda at the University of Chicago in his college course with sociologist, Harold Lasswell, a leading expert in the field during the twenties and thirties. He created radio shows such as "Kay Kyser's College of Musical Knowledge" and "The Quiz Kids." In 1941, he joined the Radio Division of the Army Bureau of Public Relations, moving over to the Foreign Information Service in April 1942. Cowan married Pauline Spiegel in 1939 and had four children, Paul, Geoffrey, Holly, and Liza.
After the war, he became vice-president for creative services for CBS TV network (1955-1958) and then president (1958-1959); director of Morse Communication Research Center at Brandeis University (1961-1965); and director of Special Programs in the Graduate School of Journalism at Columbia University in 1965. He also served at the President and editor of Chilmark Press, Inc. and chairman of the publication and advisory board of the Partisan Review.
Contents List
- Arabic Language n.d. (Box 1)
- Chinese Language ca. 1943-1944 (Box 1)
- Dutch Language n.d. (Box 1)
- English Language 1943-1944, n.d. (Box 1)
- English Language—Excerpts from Magazines & Newspapers 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  including: Arts and Letters, FYI, Review, Round-Up, Science Review, U.S. Highlights
- French Language 1943-1946, n.d., 3 folders (Box 1)
- German Language 1945, n.d., 2 folders (Box 1)
  including "Atrocities Booklet"
- Greek Language ca. 1943, n.d (Box 2)
- Icelandic Language n.d. (Box 2)
- Italian Language 1943-1944, n.d. (Box 2)
- Japanese Language n.d. (Box 2)
- Norwegian Language ca. 1943-1944, n.d. (Box 2)
- Polish Language 1944, n.d. (Box 2)
- Russian Language n.d. (Box 2)
- Spanish & [Portugese ?] Language 1943-1944, n.d. (Box 2)
- Atlantic Charter in French, Italian, German, & Greek 1941 Aug 14 (Folder 1)
- "Statement of War Aims," in English & Italian 1943 (Folder 1)
- "Declaration" in French, English & Italian 1943 (Folder 1)
- "Nouvelles Par L'Image" n.d. (Folder 1)
- "One Picture Tells the Story of Victory" n.d. (Folder 1)
- "Uniforms & Insignia of the Army of the United States" n.d. (Folder 1)
- "Map—Facts About the United States" n.d. (Folder 1)
- "ENIG OG TRO" n.d. (Folder 1)
- "Les Criminels de Guerre serant punis" n.d. (Folder 1)
- "Notiziario delle nazioni unite Bulletin des Nationa Unies" n.d. (Folder 1)
- "An American—A Man of Russian Heritage" reprinted from Woman's Dayn.d. (Folder 1)
- Photograph Posters of Pilots n.d. (Folder 1)
- "Declaration Concernant Les Buts de Guerre" n.d. (Folder 1)
- Geillustreerd Nieuws in Dutch n.d. (Folder 2)
- Communique Graphique n.d. (Folder 2)
- Communique Graphique, Nos. 3, 5, 6, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12 n.d. (Folder 2)
- "He Fights With Free Men in England" ca. 1942-1944 (Folder 3)
- Calendar in Italian 1944 (Folder 3)
- "Four Leaders of the United Nations," including F.D. Roosevelt, Winston Churchill, Joseph Stalin, & Chang Kai-Shek n.d. (Folder 3)
- "Nuwe Amerikaanse Gemeganiseerde Ruitery" in Dutch n.d. (Folder 3)
- "The Thunderbolt is Newest American Fighter" n.d. (Folder 3)
- "Thirty Tons of Crushing Power" n.d. (Folder 3)
- "The Heavy Bomber: Weapon of Decision" n.d. (Folder 3)
- "He Flies Against the Japanese" n.d.
- "Machine Gun That Goes Into a Pocket" n.d. (Folder 3)
- Four Issues of America in Russian n.d. (Folder 4)
- La Marcha Hacia La Libertad in Spanish n.d. (Folder 4)
- Il Mondo Liberno 1943 (Folder 5)
- Three Issues of Victoryn.d. (Folder 5)
- Proofs of text and illustrations for Das Dritte Reich in German ca. 1945 (Folder 6)